so today we're going to talk about the
non-acceptable
and acceptable liquids
during intermittent fasting a very
important topic because
so many people make mistakes when
they're doing fasting
and it's a lot better just to learn from
the experience of other people's
mistakes
because the amount of time it would take
for you to try to figure all this out
it would be months or years so i'm going
to show you exactly how to do it based
on a lot of experience working with
other people and even on myself now a
true fast is really not eating anything
except drinking water okay that's a true
fast now the problem with that is
the majority of the population
is has a lot less stored nutrients than
we had even 20 years ago so you're going
to experience all sorts of side effects
and problems if you don't like enhance
your fasting with certain nutrients and
there are a lot of things that you
may drink that can really nullify
your results with fasting but i want to
emphasize something when we talk about
bumping yourself out of a fast or
bumping yourself out of ketosis
or autophagy which is a condition where
you're recycling your old proteins and
you're making new proteins there's going
to be a lot of confusions
number one the benefits of fasting can
get nullified with anything that spikes
insulin so the whole goal of doing
fasting is to lower your insulin as low
as possible but there's two things i
want to bring up number one
when you consume pure fat okay you don't
trigger insulin when you consume fiber
which is a carbohydrate
you're not going to trigger insulin
your body is going to go after that fat
as its primary calories before it taps
into your own body fat
so
even though you're in ketosis
the ketones are coming from the dietary
fat not your own fat and this is why you
may not be losing weight if you consume
like a pure fat during a fast it's not
going to increase insulin it's not going
to bump you out of ketosis but it's just
going to stop your weight loss so i
created this list and we're just going
to go through it
all right number one water is that
acceptable
uh that that would be a yes
now of course there's good water and
there's bad water
tap water is just filled with chemicals
so if you
need to get a filter get one and start
using it because there are plastics
there are chemicals there are hormones
in the water supply not to mention
the toxic chemicals that they use to
kill off
germs and things in the city water so
just get a filter even if it's a brita
filter it's better than nothing
personally i have a filter that pulls
out fluoride because
if you're drinking fluoride it's going
to affect your thyroid and also in the
shower all that fluoride just makes your
skin
i mean it can create all sorts of like
red rashes and all sorts of issues and
you can simply just put a little
attachment to your shower head and
get rid of that fluoride i'll put a link
down below of a good shower head that
filters out the fluoride so spring water
is the best you can do bottled water
pellegrino is a bit expensive but it has
all the minerals and it's naturally
carbonated personally i like carbonated
water for some reason it just is i just
like it so i have a little machine that
pumps in co2 into water
and it makes my own carbonated water
but in general water is not going to
bump you out of ketosis but i would
recommend drinking a little bit more
water when you're doing intermittent
fasting if you have a tendency to get a
kidney stone you want to be consuming at
least 2.5 liters of fluid every single
day and that will really protect you
all right now what about when we add
apple cider vinegar that's a definite
yes because apple cider vinegar will
greatly help your blood sugars it's an
acid so it's going to help your
digestion so you're going to just digest
better and even now if you drink it when
you're not eating it's still going to
help your digestion and i'm talking
about the microbiome in your intestine
so it'll help that it'll also help you
absorb minerals
but the main thing it will do for you is
help your blood sugars it'll help give
you energy as well so i highly recommend
doing like a tablespoon in your water a
few times a day it doesn't actually
matter when you take it
but just try it and see if you like it
and some people use a straw so it
doesn't affect your enamel
that would be a good idea all right what
about lemon juice in your water
absolutely yes because lemon juice
has citrates and citrates help to
inhibit
oxalates so it decreases the risk of
getting a kidney stone and the lemon
juice does have vitamin c
but only if it's a fresh lemon if it's
in a lemon concentrate
it's pasteurized it's not going to have
pretty much any vitamin c at all so
the goal is not to drink it for vitamin
c the goal is to drink it to help
prevent kidney stones
by inhibiting oxalates and it's also
good for other things too it helps the
liver it helps the gallbladder and it
also has certain phytonutrients that
help in other ways all right what about
diet sodas
that would be a big fat no
because the artificial sweeteners
especially like aspartame
affects your microbiome and that can
indirectly affect your insulin levels
and create insulin resistance and that
can actually cause you to put on weight
now if you're using
diet sodas with stevia that's a whole
different story
totally fine monk fruit is another good
sweetener as well as erythrotol all
right then we get to coffee if you're
just doing black coffee it's not going
to hurt you at all so that would be a
yes on the list the only point i want to
bring up is caffeine if you're drinking
a lot of coffee through the day
you're going to be consuming a lot of
caffeine and that can inhibit your sleep
cycles which will then
increase cortisol
and that will slow down your weight loss
so i would recommend only doing one cup
in the morning
if possible that's what i do and my cup
is actually pretty small of course the
coffee is strong but it's a very small
cup i would definitely spend a little a
little bit more money and get organic
because out of all the things that are
sprayed with pesticides
coffee beans are at the top of the list
all right then we get into this
bulletproof thing what is this
bulletproof coffee well they're adding
butter or mct oil to the coffee and this
brings up the point which i talked about
in the beginning where it's not going to
bump you out of ketosis
it's going to bump you out of losing
weight if you have a slow metabolism
but i do recommend bulletproof coffee in
the very beginning while you start this
program because it's going to allow you
to do longer fasting and it has other
benefits for your cognitive ability
because mct oil and even butter will
help you generate ketones for your brain
and it's going to help you with memory
and focus and concentration but as you
get going and you're really starting to
lose weight and let's say for example
you have a slow metabolism and things
aren't happening that would be one thing
to go because i just recently had
someone that was trying to lose weight
and i they were doing one meal a day but
i noticed that they're doing uh this
bulletproof coffee so we recommended
getting rid of the fat in the coffee and
just do coffee maybe just with a little
bit of half and half of cream
and
boom they start losing weight so it is a
point to put attention on if you're
struggling with weight loss now if
you're thin and you want some extra
benefits with your cognitive function
definitely do bulletproof coffee all
right now what about half and half
versus cream
now half and half is half milk and half
cream
and then you have whole cream or
whipping cream now half and half has
maybe 1.6 grams of carbs okay so
i mean it's pretty small but it has some
in two tablespoons whereas whole cream
has zero carbs so i would always
recommend doing the whole cream in your
coffee versus half and half but it's a
real minor point so i'm going to put it
under the maybe category but that being
said
we're talking about such small amounts
and i rotate sometimes i use half and
half sometimes i use whole cream all
right then we get to bone broth
bone broth does have
protein in it it has like five grams per
cup
and that is something you don't want to
add when you're fasting so bone broth is
under the no category it's not a good
idea so it's definitely going to inhibit
your results with fasting and i just
want to back up for a second because i
forgot to talk about non-dairy creamers
wow those things are filled with
chemicals so i would avoid those at all
cost all right the next one is tea
now green tea is very good to consume
when you're doing fasting there are
certain
phytonutrients in tea even if you heat
the tea
that will help your metabolism that will
speed things up that have antioxidant
properties that have other
phytonutrients that fight cancer that
have phytonutrients that support blood
sugars and the list goes on and on and
on i highly recommend consuming some
type of herbal tea green tea is one of
them there's many others on a keto plan
but just one point about that is that
these tea sometimes have caffeine so
take that in consideration because that
can start affecting your sleep
especially if you're sensitive all right
next thing is coconut water
well coconut water has between 11 grams
to i think 16 grams
of
sugar so you definitely want to avoid
coconut water some people drink it for
hydration thinking it's a great
electrolyte drink but it comes with a
package it comes with a lot of sugar and
anytime you eat sugar or when you're
fasting you nullify your results for a
good amount of time now coconut milk
also has
some carbs
but it really depends on the type of
coconut milk
the coconut milk from brand name silk
that actually has one gram of carbs so
that may be okay
so coconut water is a no coconut milk
could be a maybe all right next one
pre-workout
powders that you put in your drink like
branched chain amino acids
not good at all we're talking about a
protein and this protein is not a
complete protein it's just amino acids
and you don't want to do that when
you're fasting okay i don't recommend
branched chain amino acids that will
definitely bump you out of ketosis it'll
bump you out of fat burning and it will
definitely bump you out of autophagy and
so even when you're working out
by consuming these amino acids or any
type of pre-workout
drink either before or after
your workout is not a good thing unless
it's just plain electrolytes with no
sugar now if you combine this low carb
diet with fasting and exercise
you're going to take your ketones to a
whole new level you'll definitely get in
much deeper ketosis and that would be a
great goal now what about alcohol okay
you've probably heard of types of
alcohol that are
so called keto friendly they have no
carbs in them here's the problem it's
true that there's certain alcohol unlike
like margaritas or a beer that have
carbs or sugar
that doesn't have any added sugar but
the alcohol itself
really
toxifies your liver which is going to
affect your fasting results and your
ability to lose weight and your
autophagy it's not a good idea in any
amounts i'm sorry now what about actual
milk is that keto friendly that would be
big fat no because milk one cup has like
12 grams of carbs and zero fiber which
means we're talking about net carbs
which is way too high but the fat from
the milk in the form of butter
as well as the half and half and cream
is a lot better
all right what about electrolytes
well absolutely yes if it doesn't have
any added sugar if it's sweetened with
stevia or monk fruit totally fine but
realize that
sometimes stevia comes with
maltodextrins so you want to make sure
it doesn't have maltodextrin or some
other type of
synthetic sugar but electrolytes are
essential when you're doing fasting
so is other nutrients like b vitamins
and vitamin d and omega-3 fatty acids
because the last thing you want to have
happen is run out of these nutrients
when you're fasting and get dizzy or
faint or feel weak so the best video
that you want to watch on that is right
here on what supplements to take while
you're fasting
you